ILGWU Miscellany 5780/061
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Miscellany
1903-1982
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/061
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Correspondence, records (documents).
5516147
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
D. Mordente, January 29, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 10, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of letters, printed material, and case files from various departments and individuals within the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Included are files of John A. Dyche, Harry Greenberg, Herman Grossman, Louis Hyman, Charles Jacobson, Edward Kramer, Charles Kreindler, Charles Baker, Rose Pesotta and Harry Uviller.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/200: ILGWU Miscellany
Women's clothing industry--United States.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--United States.; Clothing workers--United States.; Industrial relations--United States.; Baker, Charles.; Dyche, John A.(John Alexander), 1867-1938.; Greenberg, Harry.; Grossman, Herman.; Hyman, Louis.; Jacobson, Charles.; Kramer, Edward.; Kreindler, Charles.; Pesotta, Rose.; Uville, Harry.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5516147
- Research Department., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Research Department., 1921-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Research Department., 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Research Department., 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence., 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  English and Yiddish
- Correspondence., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Materials from Josephine Stern., 1903-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Research Department., 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Research Department., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- NY Coat and Suit Association., 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10a)
- NY Coat and Suit Association., 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10b)
- NY Coat and Suit Association., 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10c)
- NY Coat and Suit Association., 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- NY Coat and Suit Association. Membership Information., 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Research Department., 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
- Research Department., 1911-1924 (Box 1, Folder 13b)
- Research Department. "Justice"., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Kramer, Edward. Correspondence., 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Research Department., 1911-1924 (Box 2, Folder 2a)
- Research Department., 1911-1920 (Box 2, Folder 2b)
- Local 117., 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 3a)
  Yiddish
- Local 117., 1945-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3b)
- Minkoff, N.M. Correspondence., 1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Research Department., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 5a)
- Research Department., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 5b)
- Miscellaneous Materials., 1905-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6a)
- Bank Books. (Box 2, Folder 6b)
- Infant and Childrens' Coat Association., 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7a)
- Infant and Childrens' Coat Association., 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7b)
- Newspaper Clippings., 1913 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous., 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 1a)
- Miscellaneous., 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1b)
- Miscellaneous., 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 1c)
- Miscellaneous., 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous., 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous., 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Postcards., 1913-1916 (Box 3, Folder 5a)
- Photographs, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 5b)
- Miscellaneous., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Office of the Impartial Chairman of the Dress Industry., 1936-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7a)
- Office of the Impartial Chairman of the Dress Industry, 1952-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7b)
- Miscellaneous., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7c)
- Meeting of the Administering Board of the Dress Industry., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 7d)
- Miscellaneous., 1959-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7e)
- Registration of Trademark. "Nothing Suits Us Like Our Union Suits"., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- ILGWU Workers University. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 1 of 3], 1919-1921 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- ILGWU Workers University. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 2 of 3], 1920 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- ILGWU Workers University. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 3 of 3], 1920-1921 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- ILGWU Workers University. Vol. II. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 1 of 3], 1920-1922 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- ILGWU Workers University. Vol. II. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 2 of 3], 1922-1925 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- ILGWU Workers University. Vol. II. Syllabi and Reports. [folder 3 of 3], 1925-1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- ILGWU Workers University. Index of Lectures., 1919-1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Lectures on Practical Psychology by Dr. Samuel A. Tannenbaum. [folder 1 of 3], 1920 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Lectures on Practical Psychology By Dr. Samuel A. Tannenbaum. [folder 2 of 3], 1920 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Lectures on Practical Psychology By Samuel A. Tannenbaum [folder 3 of 3], 1920 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Lectures on Labor and Management by Leo Wolman., 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Lectures on Trade Unionism by Leo Wolman., 1920 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Lectures. [folder 1 of 3], 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Lectures. [folder 2 of 3], 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Lectures. [folder 3 of 3], 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Early Correspondence, 1907-1911 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Open Shot discharge letter, Boston 1911; Strike Disbursements, 1907
- Wanted Poster, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  New York City Police Department wanted John Giusto in relation to the William Lurye homicide